export const HISTORYA2017 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. The study of History is important because it",
A: "enables the people to remember the names of people.",
B: "informs the people about their societies.",
C: "sharpens the ability to remember dates.",
D: "teaches the students the art of storytelling.",
answer: "B. informs the people about their societies.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. Which of the following sources of history is based on mythology and hearsay?",
A: "Oral tradition",
B: "Court records",
C: "Archaeology",
D: "Ethnography",
answer: "A. Oral tradition",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. The main source of information for the study of pre-history is",
A: "oral tradition.",
B: "linguistics.",
C: "written records.",
D: "ethnography.",
answer: "A. oral tradition.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. Party manifestos, commissions of enquiry, newspapers, private letters and diaries may be classified as",
A: "artefacts.",
B: "documentary sources.",
C: "journals.",
D: "archival materials.",
answer: "B. documentary sources.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. All the following were challenges faced by the trans-Saharan traders except",
A: "constant shortage of water.",
B: "prevalence of sandstorms.",
C: "travelling in caravans.",
D: "loss of direction.",
answer: "C. travelling in caravans. (While challenging, caravans were a necessary part of the trans-Saharan trade.)",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. Which of the following was not a role played by the Taureg in the trans-Saharan trade?",
A: "Acting as guides to traders",
B: "Producing food crops to sell to the traders",
C: "Becoming administrators in the Western Sudanese courts",
D: "Acting as interpreters to the traders",
answer: "C. Becoming administrators in the Western Sudanese courts",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. The trans-Saharan trade was also known as",
A: "triangular trade.",
B: "caravan trade.",
C: "slave trade.",
D: "ivory trade.",
answer: "B. caravan trade.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. One major effect of the trans-Saharan trade was the",
A: "occupation of West African States.",
B: "development of towns and cities.",
C: "introduction of new crops into West Africa.",
D: "development of many industries.",
answer: "B. development of towns and cities.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. During the trans-Saharan trade, the articles of trade from the Western Sudan included all the following except",
A: "ostrich feathers.",
B: "dried dates.",
C: "kola nuts.",
D: "gold.",
answer: "B. dried dates.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. A major contributory factor which initially helped the spread of Islam in West Africa was that",
A: "it accommodated the traditional cultures.",
B: "there was disunity among the traditional rulers.",
C: "traditional religion was declining.",
D: "Christianity had made few converts.",
answer: "A. it accommodated the traditional cultures.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. West Africans’ knowledge of Arabic language could be traced to",
A: "their rulers’ conquest of Arab states and Kingdom.",
B: "the spread of Islamic religion to West Africa.",
C: "their efforts to establish relations with Arabs.",
D: "inter-marriages between North African traders and West Africans.",
answer: "B. the spread of Islamic religion to West Africa.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. Educated Muslims held the following important positions in the administration of many West African states except",
A: "judges.",
B: "economists.",
C: "scribes.",
D: "sailors.",
answer: "D. sailors. (Islamic scholars primarily focused on religious and legal matters.)",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. A closer contact between Western Sudan and North Africa was promoted through",
A: "Arab exploration of West Africa.",
B: "the spread of Islamic religion.",
C: "North African conquest of West Africa.",
D: "West Africans’ attempt to study Arabic.",
answer: "B. the spread of Islamic religion.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. Which of the following factors encouraged the emergence of Muslim centres in Western Sudan’?",
A: "Agriculture",
B: "Warfare",
C: "Trade",
D: "Education",
answer: "C. Trade",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. A significant effect of the European presence on the West African coastline between the fifteenth and eighteenth centuries was the",
A: "building of forts and castles.",
B: "opening of many secondary schools.",
C: "construction of railways.",
D: "opening of many clinics and hospitals.",
answer: "A. Rise and development of towns",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. A major economic reason for European interest in West Africa in the fifteenth century was to",
A: "establish many Western schools.",
B: "spread the Christian faith.",
C: "set up many factories.",
D: "trade in gold and ivory.",
answer: "D. trade in gold and ivory.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. The coming of the Europeans to West Africa in the fifteenth century led to the",
A: "decline of trans-Saharan trade.",
B: "increase in the activities of the trans-Saharan trade.",
C: "conversion of all traditional rulers to Christianity.",
D: "industrialization of West Africa.",
answer: "A. decline of trans-Saharan trade.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. The first Europeans to arrive on the shores of West Africa in the fifteenth century were the",
A: "British.",
B: "Spanish.",
C: "Portuguese.",
D: "French.",
answer: "C. Portuguese.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. The main objective of the first European explorers to reach the West Africa coastline was to",
A: "find the source of River Niger.",
B: "find a sea route to India and the Far East.",
C: "obtain enough raw materials for their industries.",
D: "find potential markets for their manufactured goods.",
answer: "B. find a sea route to India and the Far East.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. The trans-Atlantic slave trade continued after its abolition because",
A: "American plantation owners expanded their farms.",
B: "African and European traders benefitted from it.",
C: "slaves from West Africa were intelligent.",
D: "Europeans wanted to deplete the population of West Africa.",
answer: "B. African and European traders benefitted from it.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. A positive effect of the trans-Atlantic slave trade on West Africa was the",
A: "installation of new rulers.",
B: "massive importation of European firearms.",
C: "emergence of indigenous wealthy merchant class.",
D: "establishment of large plantation farms.",
answer: "C. emergence of indigenous wealthy merchant class.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. West African slaves initially sent to Europe were used as",
A: "solders.",
B: "royal guards.",
C: "charioteers.",
D: "domestic servants.",
answer: "D. domestic servants.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. The abolition of the slave trade in 1807 gave way to the promotion of",
A: "plantation farming.",
B: "legitimate trade. ,",
C: "industrialization.",
D: "gold trade.",
answer: "B. legitimate trade.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. West African slaves were sent to the Americas mainly to",
A: "work on plantation.",
B: "fight the inhabitants.",
C: "explore the hinterland.",
D: "work in the factories.",
answer: "A. work on plantation.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. The activities of the Christian missions in West Africa were initially confined to the coastal areas due to the",
A: "presence of many white missionaries.",
B: "protection given by the European traders.",
C: "hostility of some traditional rulers.",
D: "availability of fertile land for agriculture.",
answer: "C. hostility of some traditional rulers.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. Christian missionary interest in West Africa was further increased by the urge to",
A: "demonstrate their piety.",
B: "seek accommodation for the people.",
C: "stop the spread of Islam.",
D: "train the Europeans in Africa.",
answer: "C. stop the spread of Islam.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. Christian missionary activities in West Africa in the 19th century increased due to the",
A: "spread of traditional religion.",
B: "dearth of Christian priests.",
C: "rejection of Islam by the people.",
D: "growth in financial support from Europe.",
answer: "D. growth in financial support from Europe.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. Which of the following was a weakness of Christian missionary activities in West Africa?",
A: "Promotion of Western education and culture.",
B: "Stoppage of human sacrifice.",
C: "Discrimination against the Africans in the church.",
D: "The development of medical services.",
answer: "C. Discrimination against the Africans in the church.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. Apart from preaching the gospel, the Christian missionaries were involved in all the following except",
A: "setting up of schools.",
B: "establishment of hospitals.",
C: "buying the freedom of some slaves.",
D: "dethroning non-Christian chiefs.",
answer: "D. dethroning non-Christian chiefs.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. France joined the Scramble for and Partition of West Africa mainly to",
A: "recruit soldiers for her European wars.",
B: "gain territories in West Africa.",
C: "acquire fertile lands for agricultural purposes.",
D: "promote her civilization in West Africa.",
answer: "B. gain territories in West Africa.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. Which of these West African territories were annexed by Germany in 1884?",
A: "Nigeria and Ghana",
B: "Togo and Cote d’Ivore",
C: "Cameroun and Togo",
D: "Togo and Dahomey",
answer: "C. Cameroun and Togo",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. The Conference for the partition of Africa by the European powers took place in",
A: "Britain.",
B: "Germany.",
C: "France.",
D: "Portugal.",
answer: "B. Germany.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. In the colonized states of West Africa, Europeans aimed at",
A: "establishing industries.",
B: "establishing local government.",
C: "revamping the local economies.",
D: "subordinating the people.",
answer: "D. subordinating the people.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. West African states could not maintain their sovereignty after the partition of their lands because",
A: "of lack of unity among their rulers.",
B: "the Europeans were determined to take their lands.",
C: "many of the rulers did not accept them.",
D: "the Europeans promised to educate their children.",
answer: "B. the Europeans were determined to take their lands.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. West African leaders signed away their sovereignty to European nations through",
A: "treaties of protection.",
B: "military conquest.",
C: "formation of alliances.",
D: "marriage alliance.",
answer: "A. treaties of protection.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. The colonial powers promoted infrastructural developments in their colonies to",
A: "promote western education in the hinterland.",
B: "make travelling easy for the local people.",
C: "improve the lives of traditional rulers,",
D: "promote the production of cash crops,",
answer: "D. promote the production of cash crops,",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. Under the Indirect Rule System, a British District Officer performed all the following functions except",
A: "maintenance of law and order.",
B: "supervision of traditional rulers.",
C: "advising traditional rulers.",
D: "declaration of war.",
answer: "D. declaration of war.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. Many West African states were economically under-developed due to",
A: "inadequate and incompetent personnel to manage their economies.",
B: "exploitation of their resources by their colonial masters.",
C: "the absence of major industrial raw materials.",
D: "the unwillingness of their leaders to industrialize.",
answer: "B. exploitation of their resources by their colonial masters.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. The imperial power which regarded her colonies as separate entities was",
A: "Germany.",
B: "Britain.",
C: "Portugal.",
D: "Spain,",
answer: "B. Britain.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. The major way through which formal school system helped to consolidate European culture was the promotion of the",
A: "study of local languages.",
B: "use of educated elite in the government.",
C: "European mode of dressing.",
D: "study of European music.",
answer: "B. use of educated elite in the government.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. A neo-colonialist state has the outward features of sovereignty but in reality",
A: "it is subservient to the demands of its citizens.",
B: "its political leaders are irresponsible",
C: "its political policies are dictated by some powerful forces from outside.",
D: "its international relations among the comity of nations are very poor.",
answer: "C. its political policies are dictated by some powerful forces from outside.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. Most coups d’état in West Africa were caused by",
A: "corruption by public servants.",
B: "high unemployment among the youths.",
C: "ambition of some military officers.",
D: "low prices of goods.",
answer: "C. ambition of some military officers.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. One of the factors for under-development in West African states is",
A: "absence of fertile lands.",
B: "lack of professionals.",
C: "absence of infrastructure.",
D: "neo-colonialism.",
answer: "D. neo-colonialism.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. The West African leaders at independence did not record much success mainly because they",
A: "had little experience in governance.",
B: "were mostly half educated.",
C: "were interested in self-aggrandizement.",
D: "spent their time settling ethnic conflicts.",
answer: "A. had little experience in governance.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. To maintain luxurious lifestyle after leaving office, West African leaders",
A: "made many friends.",
B: "wooed investors.",
C: "built recreation centres.",
D: "embezzled public funds.",
answer: "D. embezzled public funds.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. Which of the following greatly affected West African development initiatives?",
A: "Debt relief",
B: "Endemic corruption",
C: "Political ideology",
D: "Poor education system",
answer: "B. Endemic corruption",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. The greatest financial contributor to the Economic Community of West African States (ECOWAS) is",
A: "Ghana.",
B: "Cote d’Ivoire.",
C: "Nigeria.",
D: "Togo.",
answer: "C. Nigeria.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. One major responsibility of the African Union (AU) is to promote",
A: "socio-economic interactions.",
B: "sporting activities.",
C: "conflict management.",
D: "educational standards",
answer: "C. conflict management.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. The membership of the United Nations Organisation (UN/UNO) grew significantly in the 1960’s because",
A: "of its popularity among states.",
B: "of the widespread decolonization.",
C: "of the prestige of membership.",
D: "the United States compelled more states to join,",
answer: "B. of the widespread decolonization.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. A major failure of the United Nations Organization (UNO) is its inability to",
A: "implement its resolutions effectively.",
B: "manage the World Bank and other financial agencies.",
C: "organize successful sovereign conferences in West Africa.",
D: "prevent the outbreak of epidemics.",
answer: "A. implement its resolutions effectively.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},


]